Luke here at the AR Boys YouTube channel
and me and my son Nathan we've traveled
to the Arctic and for the next four days
we're going to be catching enormous
crabs through the ice hunting tarmigan
eating amazing food ice fishing dog
sledding meeting native Craftsman and
having a great time Welcome to gome
[Music]
Alaska I was quietly detective of my
heart to reach sure that couldn't break
to pieces and be left alone once more if
you hadn't been so patient you'd be easy
to ignore you could up all my till you
didn't
any and now I stand Here calling at your
door oh now I stand
here anywhere welcome to the city of
gnome yeah I'm yours and now we're
singing all right guys welcome to gnome
we're staying here at the dredge 7 in
and we've rented a snow machine and a
Truck you ready to go get some lunch
yeah 3,700 people live here in Gnome
it's one of our bigger cities here in
Alaska and it's the largest city on the
Seward
Peninsula and Nathan do you know how
gnome got its name how when they they
first drew the map of gnome they didn't
have a name for the city yet so they
just wrote the word name and they wrote
the a sloppy and it looked like an O and
everyone thought the name was
gnome we're going to do a little ice
fishing on this trip so uh we're going
to get some fishing
[Music]
tackle oh look at that he going jig him
really aggressive just jig
him what do you think is that cool M hey
thank you
all right we got some fishing
gear gnome's famous for a number of
things one the gold rush and two the
idid rod race this right here is the
finish of the idid rod dog teams from
around the world race all the way from
Anchorage here to gnome and that's the
Finish Line 1,049 Mi it's crazy one of
the major gold rushes here in Alaska
happened here in Gnome so you'll see a
lot of gold mining stuff around town
including the world's largest gold pan
hey check it out Nathan they've got
umiacs people still use this type of
boat to hunt whales here in northern
Alaska amazing part I find fascinating
is how they're made out of wood and in
case you didn't notice there are no
trees around here traditionally a lot of
the wood came from Driftwood that they
would just find on the
shore we're going to go try airport
pizza here get some
lunch oh they have cheese fries they
have Ramen oh thank you very much
a we got a little bit of time to kill
here in our first day so we're going to
go check out the museum we're going to
get Nathan
edicated what you know edication it's
important see the little rain jackets
they make them from seal
guts you got the wallrus tusks so back
in 1925 there was a diptheria outbreak
here in Gnome and they had to get a
bunch of medicine from Anchorage all the
way to gnome and sled dogs like Fritz
here took that medicine the 1,000 miles
all the way to gnome saved a bunch of
lives so the idid rod race is kind of a
celebration Recreation of that when the
Gold Rush happened gnome became one of
those Wild West Gold Rush towns place
was hopping fish spear that's a halet
hook Nathan you want to do a little ice
fishing look
good see all these boats those are gold
ridges right there there's fine gold all
over the beaches of gnome until people
go out in the shallow parts of the ocean
and suck up the sand on the bottom and
filter out the
gold
e all right this is the small boat
harbor we're going to try to fish for
Tom Cod I don't know how thick the ice
is but it's probably several feet thick
but that doesn't mean that there's not
overflow overflow is when water pools on
top of the ice and so you can have
really deep water on top of ice this
right spot right here is where some
overflow was look at
this see right there so you don't want
to step in that and get wet you can see
two sticks in the snow over there my
guess is that's where somebody's spot is
we're going to go check that out
see there's a little bit of Styrofoam
right there you put it over the hole to
keep it from freezing try not to bust up
the Styrofoam with my
axe all right so you see there's the
hole not going to be able to cut that
open with the axe that hole is too old
going to go ahead and put this
back that hole is probably just as old
well we rented a snow machine from the
people here at dredge 7 so we're going
to go out and explore a little I brought
the 22 just in case we see some Tagan
[Music]
right now I'm on the beaches of gnome
this big sheet of ice in front of me is
the Frozen Bearing Sea these right here
are gold
dredges well me and Nathan made it up in
the mountains we're looking around for
some Target but visibility is not the
greatest but I just got a text message
from somebody who's got an augur who
says they can meet us at the harbor and
drill some holes for us to do some ice
fishing so I think we might give up on
this and uh go do a little more ice
fishing
hey oh thank you hey thanks guys
appreciate
it those are the guys that augured the
holes for us and they're headed out to
go check some king crab pots that
they've got set out under the ice out on
the ocean 15 Mi out and they said they'd
take us out tomorrow to go catch king
crab I think we need to catch some bait
first should we get some crab bait yeah
going to get out our tomod rigs all
right all right there you go that's the
bottom right there it's probably about
20 ft would you like to sit on the snow
machine while you do it something on Dad
see the little beads attract the Tom Cod
and then you go and you jerk it up and
it snags
oh oh there we
go oh there's another
one so these two little fish right here
they're called Tom Cod they don't get
much bigger than this they're just a
tiny little fish and they're really
common here in the northern oceans of
Alaska and they made good bait so I'm
standing on Frozen salt waterer the ice
here is over 3 ft
thick oh yeah I got one hold him up oh
he came off put the snow machine there
so it blocks the wind makes it a little
bit warmer and if he gets tired he has a
seat you get one good
job there we
go there you go
oh yes there you go oh I think that's
the longest one of the day Nathan yes I
got the biggest one oh that's another
good size one now we just need to do
yeah oh yeah they're a little something
different but they're also good
bait it's so
all right cover the hole up with snow
and hopefully tomorrow if we want to do
more fishing we can pop it out with the
axe it's uh end of March right now so
the sun doesn't set till 9:40 p.m. it's
already past
8:00 ready for some pizza
Hamburg Gold Rush well despite it being
so light outside we got to get to bed
we've got a lot to do tomorrow I'll see
you guys in the morning good morning
I love being in these small communities
people can leave their four-wheelers
running outside and no one going to
steal it leave their truck running with
the keys in it no one's going to steal
it all right we're going to go get some
breakfast and everyone's telling me I
should go to
pingos
good he just right
here good see right there you got the
venu you got stuffed waffles
oh
yeah oh my goodness stuff sausage that's
[Music]
nice all right Nate should we go try to
get some Tagan
uhuh came over this hill and nearly ran
over 12 tarmigan can you hear him yeah
right over
whole bunch of it see they're going to
cross up there we're off to a good start
we saw some taragan but oh they're hard
to see in this weather oh there oh yeah
there's a whole bunch more over there oh
there they are see see them right there
that's a much easier shot come
out I can see his head barely there's
one up
there we saw over a 100 Birds but we're
only able to get shots off at three of
them it's hard to see the ones that are
sitting still and the ones that are
moving are hard hard to hit if we had
strong sunlight we would have been able
to shoot a lot more I
bet what was that what was that what was
that oh we ran out of road driving along
and all of a sudden there's no more road
maintenance there's just snow on the
road got myself in the snow a little bit
deep we see if we can back out
yeah we're High centered this is the
road and I'm just driving along and all
of a sudden it gets really deep and it
was really hard to
see I don't have any shovels or tow
ropes there was a house just down the
road here going to go see if we can get
some toaster so maybe some
help all
right got a
[Music]
[Applause]
half we got
out we uh pushed a lot of snow to do
that I'm so glad he was is able to help
me I think maybe we should turn around
what do you think
yeah oh the sun's come out and it's
actually really good visibility
now this is one of the historic gold
dredges these dredges would float in the
shallow water and they would just scoop
up massive amounts of sand then process
the gold out of it then spit the sand
outout the back end these are gold
dredge buckets dozens of them on the
front of the machine and it just goes
like a chainsaw into the
ground well Nathan would you like to go
to a preschool and meet some kids yeah
all right let's do
it going to leave my knife in here
probably shouldn't bring that into the
school
hello all right thank you
byebye see you by thank you the local
people here have been so generous with
their time and showing us their
Community a few of them asked if we
could come to their preschool because
the little kids wanted to meet the
outdoor boys so I figured the least I
could do was come and say hi boys
together we want to save these chunks
for later
it is oh look at that it's not thick at
all the snow did the
trick you want to use the the ice
fishing Rock oh hey look I got one
already look at
that yeah I think this one might work
really well fight it it's fighting yep
there you
go there we go hey there another one
look at that that is such a pretty
little fish oh nice time C oh wo there
we
go all right we got plenty of Tom cods
for
bait this is the gnome Visitor Center
it's a great resource if you're trying
to do the things I'm doing here in Gnome
hi hey
Drew yeah there's the mus there's the
musx there's the name uming this is the
musx wool yeah so this stuff is hundred
plus dollar an ounce spun into wool do
you feel the heat oh Drew's been very
kind and offered to take me along when
to go pull some crab pots so would you
want to go catch some king crab you guys
got everything you
[Music]
need some this your crabs from
yesterday woohoo oh yeah there's some
Big Boys in there this is one of the few
places in the state where there's still
crab fishing down in Dutch Harbor in
that area all the fleet is shut down
because of poor numbers this is also one
of the few places in the state where you
can catch king crab with a sport fishing
license you can go get yourself a pot
cut a hole in the ice and you can go for
it make it sound so easy yep it didn't
make it that
far all right guys we're here on the
Frozen Bearing Sea if you head head that
way the next bit of land is Russia and
underneath about a foot of ice there's a
crab pot
yep a lot more crab last there's a
couple it is
solid so you got what 50 ft is that yeah
50t of rope look at
that oh look at that 2 three four yeah
hold open it up there wait there two
sish oh that's a nice one look at that
that is a nice king crab that's a blue
one isn't it no they're red king crab
that's and they got to be 5 in across is
that the yeah four and 3/4 four and
3/4 you want oh yeah hey hey
Nathan look look at that all right we'll
put him in here before he freezes up
there you
go fish I don't mean to brag but uh
there's the a Tom card oh good nice and
th all right so there's the Tom card we
caught we're turning cheap Seafood into
expensive sea food here's some rope some
oh
yeah and watch your
feet this one was the monster hole bunch
of starfish this time look at this yes
cow oh yeah yeah she's got her egg her
back in quick that looks like a decent
one yeah it
is yeah they're not popular around here
snow machine they're right now in
Anchorage king crabs about $55 a pound
so these crabs are about 3 lb each so
you're looking at about oh what 170
bucks per crab the local gnome price is
about 25 bucks for one crab that's a
good deal
There She
Goes we go there was hung there we
go there's our shirt there little shrimp
there you go look at that little shrimp
came up for the ride oh that's a nice
one Barnacle on that guy yep that's all
right oh yeah yeah here you go big old
jellyfish right there oh that think's
huge
uh-huh see a tiny little baby starfish
floating
down allar there was only one crab
between two pots they can go ahead and
move
[Music]
spots
w you look like some sort of anime
character with your overly huge sword
there
wow all the way
[Music]
now like a glove I don't know how you
guys feel about
okaying hey there we go B big crab
baby pretty good size yeah look at
that that is a beautiful one sh yeah
look at those oh it's heavy
too
good it's so easy to forget that we're
standing on Frozen salt
water so that right there guys is the
Bearing
Sea there you go the ocean currents and
Tides break the ice up and shift it
around a lot it's really easy to be on a
big solid piece of ice like this and it
to break off and drift away and you be
stranded on it I was gifted to
us thank you so much
guys those guys are so nice to let me
tag along Drew said he was going to go
cook up one of those crab for me
oh it feels good to get some warm food
in me I'm
cold there go
oh oh my goodness thank you so here
that's as fresh as it gets oh hey thank
you drew H that was so
nice
claw they kind of spiky
huh I'm going to pull it out get all
this tendons see Bend this joint
backwards what do you think of
that king crab is amazing it's got the
sweetest cleanest tasting meat of any
crab I've ever eaten and there's just so
much of it just the meat out of one leg
segment is more than like several
Marilyn blue crabs look at that
look at that chunk of body meat it's
huge oh I need to go wash my
hands oh that was the best crab I've
ever had that was really good well it's
getting late but there's one more thing
I want to do I want to go buy an ULU
knife do you want to take the truck or
the snow machine snow machine
she just
barks my crab look at a couple oh that
is nice yeah look at that these ones I
just buy exotic wood and acrylic these
ones are stainless and this is a saw
blade yeah that one soft this is the one
that my friend Willie hogendorn makes so
the these right here these are ULU
knives traditional Native Alaskan knife
well thank you very much Wilson I
appreciate it problem hey Nathan where
you at
bought a beautiful handmade ULU knife so
excited to use this thing and they gave
me a bunch of ground MUSC meat I'm going
to make burgers out of this it's going
to be
great here come on
don't it's been another lovely day but I
am tired and sore I'm going to take some
Advil go to bed and I'll see you guys
bright and early well good morning
Nathan should we get some breakfast
all
[Music]
right stopping every once in a while and
listening we can hear some and they're
way out there though
oh got one here okay come over here look
at this there some fox
tracks there you
go and there we go look at this we got
two of them well we snow machine past
where we got stuck the other day and
we're off to a great
start I think we're going to get a bunch
Nathan yeah
there's a Big Moose up on that Hillside
up there 1 2 3 4 five six moose right
here see that's a Mama moose with a calf
right there see how her hair on the back
of her neck is up and her ears are back
means she's angry she doesn't like us
she thinks we're going to hurt her baby
so let's get out of
here this old cabin with a couple Graves
out front see the cross
is we can see him right there you see
him he's still standing right there oh
see the ones in the
tree start
shooting yeah they they'll let you shoot
a lot with the
22 see hold
still my kill that's yours buddy there
you go hey Nathan high high five oh
here's the one I
got y we did
it good job buddy a shotgun and a 22 are
a deadly combo with hunting Tagan if you
see him on the ground the guy with the
22 scope can try to pick them off and if
they start to fly the shotgun can get
them all right our bags are getting
full oh the w turned out so much better
than expected but uh we're kind of high
up in the mountains now and we're just
not seeing as many Tagan or Tagan tracks
so I think we might turn around and go
back down into the
valley reverse
down something happened to our snow
machine the reverse jammed you hit
reverse and nothing happens says it's in
Reverse but it's still going forward and
it's just making this annoying beeping
sound I don't know what to do about it
but yeah I got him there's two more up
there there you go buddy you grab the
feet uhhuh all
rightel oh so Nathan's Barrel got stuck
in the snow you've got to get that
cleared out if you try to shoot a gun
that has ice and snow or mud in the
barrel it can cause the barrel to
explode all right I think we're
good open see him he's
moving when there are these huge flocks
of like a hundred as soon as one takes
off they're all take off so it's hard to
get
closed all
right oh that was a little to the left
more towards me
this just s though
like see there's one right there sure
enough it's another enormous
flock the firing pin on my shotguns
wearing down I've had it twice now where
the bullets wouldn't go off because the
PIN isn't hitting the primer hard enough
oh yeah you're right Nathan there's just
gobs of them up
there yeah there we go got another one
this is actually the Alaska state bird
this is a willow tarmigan this bird is
brown in the summertime and then in the
winter it changes to White see it's got
feathers on its toes to protect it from
the
[Music]
cold there we go got two of them
that's what hey buddy did you have fun
yeah well we ran out of time but uh I
need to clean some birds real
quick holy mackerel we got nine
birds so this right here is what's
inside all the Tagan these are the tips
of the willow trees that's what they eat
that's how they survive in the winter
time quite the bag of Tagan
meat what are you doing out here it's a
reindeer what are you doing out of here
pen rinder are a domesticated
Caribou stay out of
TR it's about 18 miles on a snow machine
woo that wind gets
cold there's a lot of uh Native alaskans
in this part of the state that carve
Ivory and I want to go check out one of
the guys here that's supposed to be
pretty good at it hi Andrew this is my
son Nathan Nathan hi how you doing
buddy out I was working this morning oh
my look at this big old walrus tusks in
the skull right there look at the got
the moulders smaller female
oh wow this is a fossilized SP here oh
yeah wow is this the F more Foss we have
oh that is so cool yeah you can't sell
it unless you're a Native Alaskan right
sell it raw or can you you can't sell it
right it has to be worked by a native
when we Harvest them or you find them on
the beach mhm you have to get these
tusks
tagged by somebody who's W Tusk tagger
you know there's a few Town look at that
oh those are sniff oh that's a nice
color in that yeah I tell you what if
you got some time and want to sand some
of the fossilized di you'd like to try
it yeah all
those come on work faster work
faster yeah that's got a great
shine so you've got a couple pieces of
Yellow Sea Glass they're putting on the
bottom of the fossilized wallers ivory
look at that that is gorgeous perfect
gift for Becca stick on oh these are the
popsockets right these are ivory
popsockets that is so sweet oh thank you
very much this is so nice it was really
nice to meet
you oh that was so much fun to see their
workshop they were just wonderful people
if you'd like to see more of their
crafts or buy some of their jewelry I'll
put a link to their website below
hey uh Nathan would you like to go dog
slitting husky
puppy well you guys got a little bit of
snow in your yard a little bit well guys
we're here at Deja Vu kenel and we're
going to do a little dog
mushing Sarah Sarah great nice to meet
you and I was I like this
I long
go and now you'll do next
one stop it in really good there you go
nice these dogs are excited they're
ready to pull all
right wo
clim our switch Yeah Yeah and then when
we're getting up the mountain I want to
switch
again all right you guys ready I'm ready
here we
go
Trail there you go you know
that's we're about to it's a fun ride
down all right we'll switch
we can give him some salmon snacks Ethan
you want to come help me give them their
snacks hold it on the edge there you go
a good boy good
job oh man I'm
you oh my goodness right now and this is
their mom so just be kind of quiet and
gentle boy little
guy don't no biting no biting bite go
for it puppies and
you this little white one really likes
your
R they're swarming
him too cute you sneak out before the
puppies come outo those guys are pretty
cute oh oh my goodness look at this snow
drift
well thank you so much for taking us out
here it's we an absolute ball awesome
hey thank you nice to meet you nice to
meet you
too K was that fun huh do you want me to
get you 15 SL dog puppies yes too
bad don't want it why we're going to get
a stuffed Caribou for Jacob and uh we're
getting this for Mama all right mama's
making out like a
bandit
yeah are pretty nice huh you like this
one you like this one there we go got a
red fox fur hat for Tommy made right
here in Gnome yeah that's right we go to
Milanos get some
dinner thank you oh hey we's going to
see
it I'll tell you what gnome is really
growing on me I like this town a
lot oh so Del the best are the Thin
Mints I so sorry we don't need a bag we
we just need more self-
discipline well we're going to bring
back a bunch of king crabs with us so we
need some Alaskan luggage this is the
luggage of Alaska right there
there you go one for you one for me you
like
do well guys this has been fun but it's
late I got to get this boy to bed I'll
see you guys in the morning good morning
I don't know about you Nathan but I want
to go back to Pingo and get some
breakfast oh yeah
thank you oh that looks beautiful Nathan
you like your
food you filling up huh
[Music]
byebye they are oh there's just tons of
them all right you want to get out the
gun
oh Nathan the gun is gone my gun is
falling
off look at
that
oh woo high
five I can't believe how quickly things
get buried in these snow
drifts woo welcome to the
Arctic I can barely see that sticking
through the
snow look at all the target
tracks there's two
there we
go see them see there's look there's two
out there on the
ice our start shooting they're getting
running away start
shooting all right there we
go
okay there two taragan were fighting
each other I just shot them both
[Music]
hey look at them they're right there
they're
everywhere
yes we out of should we go head back
yeah all
[Music]
right this thing is so full of charm
again that was Heavy those are some
super plump T again Drew's friend
Jonathan has a bunch of crabs for us and
we're going to take them home on the
plane and in case you're wondering yes
you can bring crabs on the plane if you
call them a service crab you can bring
them on as a carry-on
getting
one you want some Tagan sure check this
out oh yeah oh I'm sorry I didn't get CH
I haven't had a chance to pluck them yet
oh no no I got 5
six big quite a bit of salmon so oh
smoke salmon we you to try some oh
absolutely yes see here that's I good
GL look at that
for up to three days last night so they
wouldn't sleep that's what I was just
put that over
there hi kg hey Sean thank you so much
all
right our plane's leaving in a few hours
buddy I think it's time to pack it up
[Music]
how about
this sa
and
any change
for
I that card back to the door give some
[Music]
hugs oh we had such an amazing time we
ended up inviting over tons of family
having an an enormous Feast king crab
and Tagan and it was absolutely
wonderful and if you guys enjoyed
watching this video as much as I enjoyed
filming it make sure to click subscribe
to the outdoor Boys YouTube channel if
you like that video make sure to check
out the outdoor Boys YouTube channel
where we have hundreds of videos just
like this and if you want to see our
newest Adventures make sure to click
subscribe so you'll get notifications